It is only thanks to your generous and voluntary support that I can continue this work so a big big thank you to all of you who contribute!
Today I talk about politics, money and price control.
Come along!
I have a plan.
The character "Sickan" in the filmed crime game "Jönssonligan" always has a plan.
It is a brilliant plan Sickan, brilliant.
As with all grandiose plans, however, the league's hopes tend to be shattered, with all kinds of drops as a consequence.
Significantly less dull, but the more disastrous, however, all the history of history has been found to be the social economy.
From the totalitarian plan economies of the iron curtain to Venezuela's populist self -mutilation policy
All attempts at state control of the economy have endlessly ended in rationing, poverty and economic collapse.
It is therefore alarming that the war economy's swelling waves have now again given rise to populist requirements
on exactly this type of economic self -destructiveness in Sweden.
However, it is easy to understand the reason why these extreme ideas are again discussed,
For both inflation and higher prices, households are currently hitting all households across Europe.
Milk and eggs with 31 percent, bread with 20 percent, vegetables with 18.5 percent and meat with 17.5 percent.
At the same time, food prices are rising faster than inflation, and is also slightly higher in Sweden than in our neighboring countries.
And we have high inflation, but food prices have risen almost twice as much.
This situation now leads conspiratorial socialists to the conclusion that Sweden's food market is a dysfunctional oligopoly
that must be regulated for the good of the public.
Three players who in practice pricing and it is something that has very bad effects for ordinary families with children.
The Swedish grocery store is thus dominated by three major players, it is ICA, Coop and Axfood.
The Left Party imagines that these perceived problems should be corrected by threatening political regulation
force price controls on food.
If you think you tell these actors that if we do not get an agreement,
Then we are prepared to act politically in different ways.
It indicates well that you need to take them into a room or context to talk to them
and discuss how to hold on to these price increases
This procedure is supposed to be able to help the people, fight an unhealthy market and push back inflation
in a single hyper -efficient socialist Alexander chop.
The fact that we are higher than many comparable countries depends on the situation we have right now in Sweden.
And then we have a government in Sweden that could act but who chooses not to.
Pressing food prices it is a very important way to push down inflation broadly.
It becomes very problematic to set the idea of markets against the reality that prevails.
Despite the fact that the regulatory universal solution may appear solidarity with household's immediate needs,
In fact, this type of simple solutions to complex problems is the very definition of populism.
Therefore, let me point by point explain the real reasons for Sweden's price problems
And why the Left Party's solutions would only make everything worse for everyone.
Food prices in Sweden have increased than the throughout in the EU and more than our Nordic neighboring countries.
It is true that Sweden's food prices have risen slightly more than in the other Nordic countries.
However, the Left Party interprets this difference as that Sweden would have a unique dysfunctional food market
which can only be corrected by state regulations.
This is actually a double error.
Because in fact, the Nordic countries' food markets are very similar.
In fact, as recently as two years ago, Norway was investigated for cartel formation.
Thus, there is no big difference in the Nordic markets that would explain Sweden's higher food prices
Although a lush and more competitive food market would of course be desirable throughout the Nordic region.
However, such a competitive development is counteracted by price regulations, which instead cement the current appearance of the market
Through politically forced framework agreements that raise the market entry cost for new players.
The real reasons for Sweden's slightly higher food price costs are actually politically distorted by the left government.
But we will start tonight with food prices.
In one year, they have increased by almost 20%.
The price increase measure that Agenda refers to in this clip is the CPI
Raising the reduction obligation for fuel and the forced nuclear closures expensive Sweden's domestic production.
For several years, the agricultural sector has warned that Sweden's uniquely high reduction obligation would lead to expensive and even
Settlement of Swedish agriculture and according to the research company Energiforsk
Had Swedish energy prices been between 30 and 50 percent lower
if the left government had not forced a settlement of four nuclear reactors in southern Sweden.
In addition, the Swedish krona falls as a result of Sweden's uniquely low productivity.
Sweden's economy is going the worst throughout the EU and it is the only country where growth backs and ends up at minus.
… And this economic jumbop placement is in turn a result of both an careless monetary policy and unbudged integration costs.
Thus, it is not a capitalist conspiracy that is behind Sweden's comparatively larger food price increases
Without the fact that Sweden's left -wing government consciously carried out a policy that expensive both domestic production and imported goods.
In the rear view mirror this can be described as the trinity of the "regulatory stupidity",
Where power -hungry Social Democrats first became dependent on regulatory environmental parties,
which together then regulated higher energy prices whose consequences The Left Party now wants to handle with price regulations.
This strategy is like first drilling holes in the boat, then blaming the crew for sinking,
And with the nose over the water finally requires a ban on drowning accidents.
To try to regulate regulations with more regulations in this way in an almost poetic manner
The unmatched path of socialism towards societal collapse.
I will now explain exactly how this goes in ten simple steps
In a free market, the price of a product is regulated by supply and demand.
If many want to buy a certain item rises its price
Because this tells the producer: "If you can't produce this to be cheaper than this, it must not be sold."
This means that less is produced by the product, even though demand continues to increase.
Price regulation has now created a deficiency.
In order to compensate for the deficiency created by price regulation, the state is now beginning to subsidize the production of the product.
This, in turn, knocks out other producers of the product, who cannot compete with the state's tax subsidized production.
Now the state's forecasts and tax capital control all production of the product,
But because the pattern of consumption is irregular, unpredictable over and deficits, which means both queues and waste.
In order to balance this unpredictability, people begin to hoard the goods, and black markets arise beyond the control of the state.
As a result of the growing black market, the social economy begins to stagnate,
And the state must invest more resources in both the price -regulated product and on fighting the black markets.
The state's cost to manufacture the goods is therefore constantly rising, while the regulated price is firm.
This leads to the entire economy starting to collapse.
Due to the price regulation, the state's costs for the production of the product are now unsustainable,
The state is now starting to regulate more and more prices increasingly harder to cover its rampant production costs,
At the same time as the economy is shrinking in an accelerating vicious circle.
Finally, the economy collapses completely and when society is crashed into misery and poverty, capitalism is blamed.
These ten points depict how exactly all socialist countries in history have collapsed.
This is so basic,
So accepted and so empirically well -placed that everyone who has read economics at the upper secondary level can account for its relationship.
This is probably also why Sweden's Perplexa Finance Minister could not explain to Camilla Kvartoft
Why price regulations lead to deficiency: because the connection is so obvious that it would be like suddenly being held accountable for why
gravity would cause objects to fall to the ground.
So if Sweden's financial situation is partly self -inflicted and cannot be corrected with price regulations
What should one really do
It is telling that both the Left Party's economic spokesperson Ali Esbati and party leader Nooshi Dadgostar
Completely dismisses the 75 years of consistent economic empiricism that contradicts their market interventionist policy.
But that would not have any good effects, says Lars Jonung if you introduced price ceilings.
But Lars talks about long historical events, many situations that have divorced dramatically
And as there is still debate.
There is a shortage, it also becomes bureaucratic, many economists think this is a bad idea simply,
That you should not go in and control a market that way.
There are many economists who also perceive that it is not.
But outside the left's most pure study circles in Marxist revolutionary theory, there is no debate that planning economics does not work.
It is also telling that some on the left flank now compare the ambition to lower the tax on fuel with price control
Because it only shows how little this movement actually knows about finances.
Namely, lowering a tax is essentially different from introducing a regulation,
Then the former liberates the market forces so that they can correct
If you appreciated the content of this video it helps a lot if you share it with your friends
And supports my work through one of the payment methods below.
Feel free to share your own opinions and experiences in the comments field but I ask you to always be polite.
I do not accept aggression, person assembly or racism in my idea -driven comment fields.
Thank you for commenting to respect this
My name is Henrik Jönsson, and I want to inform that price regulations are an empirically proven lousy strategy.
Thanks for me, and thank you for listening